Finding Aid for Carl McIntire Collection 1933-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carl McIntire Collection 1933-1993, 1960s-1970s
McIntire, Carl, 1906-
3 linear feet
Fundamentalist clergyman, founder of the International Council of Christian Churches, editor of the Christian Beacon; sermons, tracts, books and other materials written by McIntire; some photographs and a cassette tape.
88538 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection has been donated to the library in multiple accessions beginning in 1970 by Carl McIntire (donor no. 4984 )
The collection is open for research.
Carl McIntire was born May 17, 1906 in Ypsilanti, Michigan, where his father, Charles Curtis McIntire, was pastor of First Presbyterian Church. By 1908, however, the family had moved west, and McIntire spent his early years in Oklahoma. Originally aiming for a career in international law, McIntire spent three years at Southeastern State College in Durant, Oklahoma. However, possibly influenced by his missionary parents, McIntire spent his senior year at Park College, a Presbyterian school in Parksville, Missouri. Here McIntire made the decision to enter the ministry. After graduation from Park College in 1927, McIntire entered Princeton Seminary to continue his theological training.
McIntire arrived at Princeton in the midst of the modernist-fundamentalist struggle. When Princeton reorganized in 1929, McIntire, already a staunch fundamentalist, followed New Testament scholar J. Gresham Machen to Philadelphia, where Machen and other former Princeton faculty established Westminster Theological Seminary. McIntire graduated from Westminster in 1931 and in that same year married Fairy Eunice Davis, whom he had met while a student in Oklahoma. Ordained in the Presbyterian Church USA (PCUSA), McIntire became pastor of Chelsea Presbyterian Church in Atlantic City, New Jersey. In 1933, however, McIntire was called to the pastorate of Collingswood Presbyterian Church in Collingswood, New Jersey, where he would spend the remainder of his professional life.
Early in his ministry at Collingswood, McIntire established the agencies and attitudes that would hallmark his lifelong career as America's militant voice of fundamentalism. In 1934, McIntire accepted an invitation to serve on the board of the Independent Board of Foreign Missions, founded some years earlier by J. Gresham Machen in an effort to insure biblical teaching in Presbyterian missions. When in 1936 the PCUSA demanded that PCUSA-ordained clergy resign from the independent agency, McIntire (along with Machen, and others) refused. The PCUSA responded by defrocking the dissenters; McIntire's church then voted to leave the PCUSA, and McIntire resigned from the Presbytery. McIntire and his congregation then joined with Machen and other deposed congregations in forming a more fundamentalist Presbyterian denomination, which they called the Presbyterian Church in America (this body later became the Orthodox Presbyterian Church). By 1937, however, the new denomination itself was rife with conflict. Severely disagreeing with Machen on various matters of doctrine and practice, McIntire left the PCA and founded the Bible Presbyterian Church, headquartered then, as now, in Collingswood.
From the beginning, the Bible Presbyterian Church, militant advocates for biblical orthodoxy, took a strong stance of ecclesiastical separation, calling for separation not only from apostasy, but also from all who would have any affiliation with individuals and groups whom the BCP considered apostate. Destined, it would seem, to a life of controversy and conflict, McIntire and other separatist fundamentalists established coalition groups in opposition to similar groups organized by mainstream liberal and moderate denominations. In 1941, in opposition to the ecumenical Federal Council of Churches (forerunner of the National Council of Churches), McIntire formed the American Council of Christian Churches (ACCC).
In similar protest "against the tenets of modernism" and in an effort to "proclaim the doctrines of the faith of the Reformation," in 1948 McIntire, members, and supporters of the ACCC met in Amsterdam to form the International Council of Christian Churches. This council, formed in opposition to the World Council of Churches (WCC) which was established in Amsterdam in the same year, continues to be headquartered in Collingswood, New Jersey, supported by McIntire and the Bible Presbyterian Church.
In the 1950s McIntire's extremist views again led to schism. In 1956 the Bible Presbyterian Church split; the majority of members turned away from McIntire and reorganized as the Bible Presbyterian Church, Columbia Synod. McIntire, with supporting congregations in New Jersey, California, Kentucky, and Tennessee, continued as the Bible Presbyterian Church, Collingswood Synod. At the same time, controversy over McIntire's administrative style and commitment to militancy broke out in the American Council of Christian Churches. Eventually, in 1968, Council members failed to support McIntire's leadership, and in 1969, McIntire left the ACCC and subsequently formed the rival American Christian Action Council.
The seeds of the Twentieth Century Reformation Hour, the media "arm" McIntire established in the 1950s, were sown in 1936 when McIntire began publishing the Christian Beacon, a weekly paper designed to "carry religious news that didn't seem to be getting into the press." Though specific topics would vary with the news of the day, the Beacon's "one over-all subject [was] the defense of the Faith...." In the 1930s and 1940s, the Beacon focused its attention on ecclesiastical modernism, especially that which McIntire and his followers saw in the National Council of Christian Churches and the WCC. In the 1950s, however, McIntire's focus went beyond the WCC to what he saw as the source of its ever-increasing apostasy: Communism. Consequently, from the 1950s into the 1980s, McIntire dedicated his ministry to the militant, vociferous exposure of "Communist infiltration of religion and the inroads being made into the churches by liberal theologians who deny the basic creeds of Christian belief."
The Carl McIntire collection consists entirely of printed materials which fit three general classifications: books, sermons, pamphlets, etc. written by Carl McIntire; newsletters, special reports, and other materials written by Carl McIntire and/or associates, as part of the work of the Christian Beacon Press and the Twentieth Century Reformation Hour; and various publications by or about many of the agencies established or supported by the Bible Presbyterian Church.
Though the collection spans the years 1933-1993, the bulk of the materials date from the 1960s and 1970s. Even so, there is sufficient chronological representation to enable the researcher to trace the development of McIntire's opposition to Communism and its various manifestations as he saw them in ecumenism, the American civil rights movement, opposition to the Vietnam War, and other key issues of the era.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Civil rights.; American Council of Christian Churches.; Bible Presbyterian Church. Collingswood Synod.; Capitalism--United States--Religious aspects.; Catholic Church.; Christian Beacon; Church and state--United States.; Clergy--New Jersey--Political activity.; Communism.; Conservatism.; Ecumenical movement.; Fundamentalism.; International Council of Christian Churches.; McIntire, Carl, 1906-2002.; Modernist-fundamentalist controversy.; National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America.; Patriotism--United States.; Prayer in the public schools--United States.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; World Council of Churches.
Subjects - Visual Material:
McIntire, Carl, 1906-2002.
Contributors:
Christian Beacon Press.; International Council of Christian Churches.; Twentieth Century Reformation Hour (Organization)
Sound Recordings
McIntire, Carl, 1906-2002.; Sermons--American.; Bible Presbyterian Church of Collingswood (Collingswood, N.J.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal
  The Personal series includes biographical material and publicity for various rallies and marches led by Carl McIntire. There are also a few photographic portraits of McIntire.
  - Photographs (portraits of McIntire) (Box 1)
  - Biographical file (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Publicity for rallies (Box 1)
- Printed Works 1933-1993
  Printed Works includes sermons, books, pamphlets, and other materials written by McIntire
  - Books 1938-1983
    - A Cloud of Witnesses, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Twentieth Century Reformation, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Rise of the Tyrant, 1945 (Box 1)
    - "Author of Liberty" 1946 (Box 1)
    - Modern Tower of Babel, 1949 (Box 1)
    - The Struggle for South America, circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - The Battle of Bangkok circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - The Wall of Jerusalem Also Is Broken Down 1954 (Box 1)
    - Better Than Seven Sons, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Servants of Apostasy 1955 (Box 1)
    - Epistle of the Apostasy, 1958 (Box 1)
    - The Death of a Church, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Outside the Gate, 1967 (Box 1)
    - God of All Comfort, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Freedom Is My Business, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Other works
    - Broadsides and tracts 1951-1983 (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets and booklets 1935-1983 (Box 1)
    - Sermons and addresses 1933-1983 (Box 1)
    - Sermons and addresses 1988-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Professional Affiliations 1930s-1987
  Professional Affiliations, which includes materials concerning agencies established by Carl McIntire and the Bible Presbyterian Church. Of these the Twentieth Century Reformation Hour sub-series is by far the most complete. A full linear foot, the TCRH sub-series contains nearly twenty years of newsletters, special reports, letters to the TCRH "radio family," and numerous other publications addressing such topics as Communist infiltration, ecumenism and apostasy, capitalism and individual freedom, the "menace" of Roman Catholicism, the American civil rights movement, the Vietnam War, and prayer and Bible reading in public schools. (These, also, form the topics of materials in the Printed Works series.)
  - Atlantic City Christian Association (Box 2)
  - Bible conferences (Box 2)
  - Bible Presbyterian Church (Box 2)
  - Christian Beacon Press (Box 2)
  - Faith Theological Seminary (Box 2)
  - International Council of Christian Churches
    - Miscellaneous publications 1944-1972 (Box 2)
    - Congress publications 1954-1973 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Shelton College (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Reformation Hour 1960-1977
    - Commemorative booklet 1975 (Box 2)
    - Ecumenical Coloring Book (Box 2)
    - Letters to "radio family," 1961-1970 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Broadsides, tracts, and pamphlets 1961-1975, undated (Box 2)
    - Booklets 1960-1987 (scattered), 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Special reports 1960-1977, undated, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Weekly news commentaries 1960-1970, 7 folders (Box 3)
- Sound Recording
  - Sermons delivered at Bible Presbyterian Church in Collingswood, New Jersey June 25, 1995, 1 audiocassettes (Box 3)